So today's lecture is going to
be about planning and multi-step
reasoning.
So today's lecture, we are
going to cover three papers
on multi-step
reasoning and planning.
Let's start with this paper
from ICML of last year.
So the title of the paper is
Language Agent Tree Search
Unifies Reasoning Acting and
Planning in Language Models.
So the types of
applications that we
want to target in
multi-step tasks
are tasks that we not only
need to reason about things,
but also need to act through
those reasoning steps
and search our trajectories,
or optimize trajectories
and how we get to a
final correct answer.
So in the reasoning
step, the model
needs to think about
what needs to be done?
For example, what the budget
is, where the plan is.
These are the reasoning steps
for a trip or vacation planning
prompt.
The act is OK.
Now that you have certain
types of reasoning or thinking,
how do you gather
more information,
or act on these reasoning steps?
For example, the action
could be a browsing
the web, generating
a query to search,
read Reddit, or a
travel blog, and so on.
And then another step is search.
Given these feedback,
or the information
that's gathered online, how
can we refine our plan so far?
Maybe we can consider
alternative destinations, search
new things to do while
we are there, and so on.
So there are a series of
reasoning, action, and search
steps that needs to be done
to solve this problem of,
for example, planning a trip.
So the problem, or the challenge
that this paper specifically
wanted to address
was the following.
The goal here was, let's go
from the LLM, generate a plan,
and executing on that
plan, to really try
to encourage diversification and
exploration of different types
of plans, or paths that the
model can take because models--
And this is true still
to this day, that
creating a diversity of
solutions, or acting upon them
and planning multiple
steps of optimization
to reach a solution.
So this paper focused on
bringing known techniques
from reinforcement learning
and multi-step planning that
existed in the past, including
multi-step Monte Carlo tree
search into the
LLM reasoning path.
And given that the models
can take feedback in,
it also introduced
ways for the model
to take different feedback
as the model explores
with the environment
and bring that back
in order to refine and optimize
future plans and search
processes.
So just a quick example
of how this worked.
For example, the prompt is
to plan a trip to Hawaii.
There are different ways
and different actions
that the model can take,
so it can, for example,
if we sample the
model for this prompt,
the model might decide
that we might consider
asking friends that
already went to Hawaii,
or read subreddits
related to that.
And then this framework
introduced a mechanism
for getting a score for
each of these actions,
and then update the search
space, or the trajectory
of follow-up expansion of
this tree that is being
formed based on that score.
And we talk about how
these scores are generated.
In this case, action
1 has a higher score,
so we expand that action, so
the model expands that action.
So in this case, ask two
friends, friend a and friend
b, about opinions,
and then based
on the quality of responses,
their score for that,
and the model can
expand from there,
so there is a flavor of
multi-action sampling
in this case.
The actions can, in fact,
be executed in parallel.
Like these two actions,
or these two actions,
they both can be
executed in parallel.
And there's this notion of let's
do continuous exploration based
on the best state,
but also consider
a mix of exploration
and exploitation,
and that's where
the MCTS comes in.
So there are two papers that--
this paper was basically saying,
how it diverges from those.
Math-Shepherd is a paper
that we saw previously,
and in that paper,
there was a verifier
that was guiding the search
process in the test time.
Basically, the
reasoning trajectories
are scored by this verifier,
and then the expansion
is guided by that.
But in LATs, which
is this paper that we
are going to learn more
about in this lecture,
this scoring is not based
on reasoning theorists,
but it's based on the
outcomes of the actions
that the model takes.
And also there is this part
about reflection of the model
to evaluate how this
trajectory went,
and also about the observations
from the environment.
It also improves based on
previous methods frameworks
on reasoning such as the ReAct
work, where basically in ReAct,
there is this extra step up.
We are going to
see how this works,
but there is this extra step
memorization, and, again,
reflection and an interaction
with the environment
that we have in the LATs paper.
And specifically, we
have more and more
planning into the process.
So here is the
intuition behind LATs.
There is the chain of
thought, where the reasoning
process is basically decomposed
into a number of steps.
There is this notion
of tree expansion.
Basically, through these
types of actions, that action
generation that we have, we have
a tree, that we form a tree,
and we do search and
planning through that.
And then we have
this borrowed that
from the ReAct framework, where
the feedback from these actions
are incorporated
into this search
process for the future
search and so on.
So this method concretely has
six types of stages, selection,
expansion, evaluation,
simulation, back propagation,
and reflection, so let's see
exactly how this method works.
And let's walk through
an example prompt.
So in this case, the prompt
is navigate through a maze
to reach an exit.
And then the initial
observation is
that you're in a
dimly lit room, there
are two doors, one on the
left and one on the right,
and the goal is to reach
an exit in this case,
so let's see how these different
steps of LATs come into play.
So first is the
selection process.
In this stage, we need to
select a node to expand.
Let's say, we have done that.
We see exactly how
that's done, but given
that we have selected a node,
and this is based on UTC,
we are going to
see it in a bit, we
want to see what actions that
we can take from that node.
So in this case, our
initialize node is this thing,
you're in a dimly
lit room and so on.
Now, let's say, the model
samples different actions here.
In this case, three
actions are sampled.
One is open the left
door, open the right door,
and the third one is
inspect the room for clues.
Then the next step is
each of these actions
are executed in the environment,
and the observation is basically
appended to the context.
So in this case, say, if the
action is open the left room,
the observation is dark
corridor with paintings.
Action B is open the right.
There is another observation
and so on for action C.
Now comes the evaluation.
So let's say, we have an action,
we have executed an action,
we want to evaluate our new
state that we are going into.
For this part, they suggest
averaging for creating a score.
Based on the current
action and observation,
they suggest adding up
two scores together.
One is using an LM score,
basically using LLM-as-a-Judge
and prompting the model for
evaluating how promising this
state is, and literally asking
it to give a score based on 0
to 1 for this state.
And the other one is the
self-consistency score.
And that is, let's assume
instead of three actions here,
we had sampled 50 times.
We had sampled 50 actions,
and we categorized them
into different types of actions.
And if an action
is sampled more,
we give a score
corresponding to the rate,
or the frequency of an
action being sampled.
So in this case, the
self-consistency score
for state A was higher because
75% of the time maybe the action
was sampled, so the
way to create just one
value for this action
is to add up these two.
So now we have a value
for action A corresponding
to state s_A.
And then we have
the simulation part.
For example, in a greedy
method from the previous stage,
we have s_A having
the highest score.
s_B and s_C have
much lower scores,
so we go and expand
s_A all the way begin.
We can continue this process.
We sample more from s_A
and we continue expansions
until we reach an end state,
or whether it's successful,
or it fails, or until we
reach the budget that we have
for expansion of this state.
So in this case,
from state s_A--
so this was s_A, and then we
have the candidate actions
that start from that state.
And then in this
case, it's greedy.
It takes one action
approach, this staircase,
and then we reach an
observation, which
we are lucky in
this case, we have
the exit door clearly marked.
We got a point here.
And then let's say the
simulation is done.
We either have a
successful trajectory
or it's a failure, then we can--
the important part
here is how do we
use this observation
to backprop and update
the scores that we had
for different actions
that were taken?
So this is the backprop
stage, and then
that is used to influence
the score of each state,
and we're going to
talk about it in a bit.
Let's talk about how these value
function and backpropagation
is used.
So for the value function,
we already saw that.
That is a weighted average of
asking an LLM-as-a-Judge given
this observation, this action,
what are the chances of success?
Give us a score between 0 to 1.
And then there is
the self-consistency,
which basically we just count
how many times a given action is
sampled.
Then there is the notion of
UCT, or upper confidence bounds
applied to trees.
That's something that this
basically the number, or score
that is used for selection
because at each point,
we have a range of values
that we want to see,
which node we go and expand.
So the way UCT works, and
this is completely borrowed
from the MCTS literature.
The way it's designed is to try
to balance between exploration
and exploitation.
If we just go based on the
highest value at that point,
we might miss out other
nodes that right now, maybe
at the current moment
have a lower value,
but down the road
at the end might
have higher value, so let's
balance the two of them.
So the way UCT works is that it
has this exploitation one, which
is V of s, plus
a hyperparameter,
times this other term, which
encourages exploration.
And the way this work
here is that the Np is
the number of times a
parent of a node is visited,
and Ns is the number of nodes
that this current node is,
not the parent, but the
current node is visited.
And basically, think
about it this way.
Relative to the parent node,
if a node is visited less,
we want to encourage
visiting that node more.
And if that node
relative to the parent
is visited a large
number of times, then
this number, this division, this
becomes a smaller number and UCT
becomes lower relative to
unexplored children of a parent
node.
So UCT, again, is the number
that we use for selection
of a node and going from there.
Now, back propagation,
and that's
where we go at the
end of a trajectory,
either we succeed or fail.
The return of that trajectory
is used to update the values,
and this is like back
propagated through the steps.
So at each point,
the value of a state
is the value of the old state,
times the number of visits
to that node, minus
1, plus the return,
divided by the total number
of visits to that node.
So that's how the math
behind this framework.
Yes.
Why does it have one [INAUDIBLE]
you take a long time,
but it didn't take long?
It's just something.
There's some math and
theoretical intuitions
behind it.
There is no proof that
this is the optimal round,
but you want to just
balance the two in that this
is considered a more
optimized way of doing things.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
So once backpropagation
is done, they also
append this reflection
of the model itself
about the trajectory
that was expanded.
If it fails or it
succeeds, the model
adds some thinking
behind what happened,
what led to the failure or the
success of this trajectory,
and this apparently
has been very
helpful in overall increasing
the quality of this approach.
So they tested this
approach on HotPotQA,
which is some data set that we
use it for multi-step reasoning
optimization.
Basically, the way
this data set works
is that for each question
for answering them,
you need retrieval from, at
least, two different Wikipedia
pages because it's just
designed like that,
so you need this multi-step
by design process
in order to find an answer.
And they're doing really well.
Just look into in terms
of as they increase
the number of samples or
the number of trajectories
that they sample,
they can significantly
improve performance,
and the reflection
and bringing those reasoning
traces also gives a lot of boost
at the end to the model.
So basically, they have
provided a mechanism
to translate more
compute at test time
effectively to better solutions
for this multi-step reasoning
tasks.
They also tested
that on WebShop,
which is this interesting data
set for practical applications.
This is just to
show you an example
of how this data set works.
For example, there is--
I'm looking for a small
portable folding desk
that's already fully assembled.
It should have this color
and this finish and so on,
and the price is--
so it's by design,
it's a multi-step
process, and they're
showing that their approach
without any fine tuning.
And just at test
time, they can get
really high results, even close
to human experts in this case.
So to summarize,
what LATs proposed
was a new technique for
bringing in reasoning,
taking actions and
planning all together,
and brought in our
known ideas like MCTS
into the language model world.
And they got very strong
results on multiple domains.
And given their
test time approach
and the modular approach,
it's very portable
and relatively easy to create.
The downside, of
course, is the cost.
Each of these back
propagation and expansion
of a tree, all of those
are adding a lot of cost,
and the cost benefits was not
really analyzed in the paper.
Another assumption that
this paper didn't address
was really that
there are scenarios,
where taking an action
may be irreversible.
So that's going to
be challenging like,
how do we adapt to
those scenarios,
if, for example, the model
is running a transaction?
If it actually
takes those actions,
it could be very consequential,
like paying for a service
and so on.
So that is another scenario,
where this approach might not
be adaptable to.
So here, there are
a few questions
about this paper that I really
would like you to think about it
maybe for a couple
of minutes, and then
we discuss anything related
to where you see the strengths
or weaknesses of
this paper, or if you
were to adapt it or extend
it, how would you do that?
So let's start doing that,
and I'll get back to you
in a couple of minutes.
All right, let's get back.
Anyone wants to
comment on this fork?
So the UCT method is basically
like upper confidence-bound
from banded learning
setting, right?
There's other algorithms for
embedded learning like picking
and exploring various arms.
Did they try different
ones in this paper?
The question is UCT is one way
to create this exploitation,
but there are a
lot of literature,
now that whether they compared?
Yeah.
No, and there is
that whole literature
of multi-armed
bounded and other ways
that we can bring in
exploration, exploitation
into the optimization
process, and all of that
could be also explored here.
Their main contribution
is that created a platform
that now others can
bring in other approaches
to optimization.
Yeah.
Anything else?
Questions or comments?
OK, let's move on
to the next paper.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, go ahead.
If we want to keep track
of the action trajectory
based with the Monte
Carlo tree search, what
if there are times when there's
repeated actions like action AB,
AB is, or when the same action
is seen in multiple nodes,
is there any way to
optimize this tree,
or does this tree recognize
all of these repeated actions
as independent trajectories?
So the question is, if a
series of actions are repeated,
how do you--
so the philosophy behind this
is that if an action is repeated
inside a trajectory,
given a parent node,
you would increase the
count of that action,
and that comes in
the UCT formulation.
So ideally, you would
capture in that as you
are forming this tree.
And ideally, this is a
tree that you're forming.
Not some fully
connected graph, so this
is the assumption behind this.
Yes.
So let's now talk about SPRINT.
This is a NeurIPS 2025 paper, so
this hasn't been even presented
here at the conference.
So this paper is about,
again, it gives you
a flavor of this
planning and parallel
execution of those
plans and how we
can use the model itself to
enable it to think better
in parallel, and we
can optimize that.
So this paper, SPRINT, was
motivated by this observation
that the reasoning
models such as o1, Gemini
Think, Gemini 2.5 Pro, and
pretty much all the frontier
models right now, they have
this tendency that for harder
problems, they think more.
And this longer thinking
corresponds to higher accuracy,
so these models to think
for longer and longer
like chain-of-thoughts.
For example, these
two graphs here
show that the DeepSeek-R1
during the training process.
As the training
process continues,
obviously, it becomes
better at solving
this, Amy, these math problems.
But also, if we take a look at
the average length per response,
that is also going
up, so it seems
like there is a correlation
between model thinking
for longer and a
larger sum of number
of tokens and the accuracy
that we get from that.
Now, again, so the
observation here
was that these long
reasoning steps are helpful,
but at the same time, many
of these reasoning steps
seem to be independent
of each other.
For example, the model tries
alternative approaches,
it decomposes a task into
subtasks that some of them
can be run in parallel, and
then some of these steps
are verifying the
previous steps.
But there is a lot of-- if
we look into the graph that
describes the
reasoning trace, there
are parts of these
computations that
are independent of
each other, so we
don't need to really wait
for all of these steps
to be created
sequentially by the model,
so we want to see how we can
leverage this parallelism
observation.
And so the idea is,
we want the model
identify this parallelization
opportunities and act on it.
So SPRINT is a
framework that does
come in during the post-training
and/or fine tuning process,
and what it does is that
it takes a reasoning model
and enables the reasoning
model to execute the response
generation.
We are a planner that
creates a set of plans
for how to approach solving a
problem and a set of executors,
and those executors can be
run in parallel in order
to carry out the plan.
And this can happen
again and again.
We can have the next slide.
We can have a plan, a
bunch of execution plans
that are carried
out in parallel,
and then we can have
another set of plans
and then another set
of parallel executions,
so the interleaving of
these planning and execution
is what it can enable
acceleration of the reasoning
process.
So let's see how we can
enable the model to create
these parallel traces.
And this is
something that I want
you to think about it
beyond just this paper,
and we're seeing it
in the following work
that we are talking about.
A lot of times when we want
to create data and figure out
a certain behavior
in the model, we
can use the LLMs itself in
the fine tuning data creation
process, and here is
an example of that.
Given a reasoning model's
response trajectory
to a question, we
can decompose it
in a number of steps via an LLM.
So in this case, for
example, we had DeepSeek-R1
generate these reasoning
traces and responses
to these questions.
And then we had a
model like GPT-4o
going through this
reasoning trace,
and annotate the steps of
the reasoning response.
And not only that, for
each of these steps,
we ask the GPT-4o to
annotate whether which
part is the planning part, and
which part is the execution
part.
And in some steps, there were
multiple execution pieces
for a given plan.
So for example,
we had this query,
we had the reasoning
trace, and then
there are a bunch of things
that needs to be done.
And then when the reasoning
stops, there is a final answer.
Then we use GPT-4o to
go through this process
and create these
steps 1, 2, and k.
Basically, now we have
these annotations,
and within each
step, the model also
annotates the plan
and the execution.
Which part is the planning part?
Which part is the
execution of that plan?
Given that, then we can
create a DAG of these steps.
So we have step 1 and
step 2 and all the way,
and we can, again,
use the model.
And the model does a
really good job here
of saying whether how these
steps are related to each other.
For example, step 4 and 2 are
not dependent on each other,
but they both depend on step
1-- is a follow-up to step 1,
so now we have a DAG of an
optimizer and basically,
creating the DAG that describes
how this reasoning trace works.
And then we can do
packing of these steps.
For example, step 1
can be done first,
and step 2 and 3 can be
done completely in parallel
with each other and so on.
And once we have these data
set that we have annotated,
then LRM here is just a
large reasoning model.
Basically, all LLMs are now
inherently reasoning models,
so what we are creating
here is this data set
of the steps, plan, and
executions in parallel,
and we basically fine tune
the model, for example,
DeepSeek-R1 to now
think in that way.
So previously, we would
just create those inherently
have these
properties, but now we
want the model to think
more and more in parallel
by showing these parallel-like
planning and execution traces.
And we just fine tune the model.
In this case, just a
supervised fine tuning
of basically showing the
model the same stuff,
the same thinking processes, but
now annotated with these texts.
And this helps the model
that at inference time, now,
the model can output these tags.
For example, here
is plan 1, and then
here are the execution
patterns for this.
And here is plan 2, and so on.
So, for example,
for plan i, there
is a set of thinking
and a parallel execution
that the model just
outputs itself,
and then we can
go over executing
these plans in parallel,
and then syncing the output
and returning the context.
And then the model goes
through plan i plus 1,
and then there is a number
of parallel subplans
within that the model can
output and we can go from there.
Why this matters?
So the cost of LLM
inference, especially when
we get to multi-step reasoning,
becomes a huge burden.
And you might have already
noticed that yourself,
and you spend a lot of time
waiting for the model to output
the response it gets.
It might make you not happy,
you want the answers fast,
but also it's a lot of costs
and a lot of delay that
goes into generating
these responses.
So right now, here is how
the sequential reasoning
models work, so there is
a query, there is a plan,
and then execution of that plan.
There's plan 2, execution
of plan 2, and so on,
so this is the
time that it takes
to generate, or go over
this thinking process
and generate the final answer.
But if we could leverage
this independence
from plan 1 and plan 2, we
could have the model execute.
We could have the
execution of those plans
be done at the same time.
Here is what after we
fine tuned with the spring
at inference time happens, so
instead of model generating
plan 1 and executing that,
then generating plan 2,
model generates these two
plans first, plan 1 and 2,
and then it starts executing.
The execution of those plans
happen at the same time.
And then the execution
could be using a tool.
For example, the model is
come up with a calculation,
and then we can use
this calculator Python
to execute plan 1 and
plan 2 and so on and then
go to the next stage.
And the fine tuning
data, again, this
is another visualization of how
given these annotations that we
have for plans and execution,
we create the fine tuning data,
so we are basically
asking the model
to think in parallel,
if the plans are
independent of each other.
We are basically teaching the
model to come up with plan
1 and 2 at the same
time, because they're
independent depend of each
other and we execute them.
Yes.
So if there's a need
for a replaning,
how does the model
remember which
plans correspond to
which executions, and all
of those things?
Later in the infant stage,
after the execution for someone
who realizes that, oh,
what I did was wrong.
How does it remember to
do a replanning of go
to the plan of 3
instead of plan of 2?
So this fork, you're bringing
the previous work in here.
Here, the model can-- so what
we are teaching the model
here is that to think about
plans at each point of time,
even if it's a revision
of an existing plan.
If it can generate plans that
can be executed in parallel,
it should do so.
It should not wait for
the execution of plan 1
to generate plan 2, because
plan 2 is independent of plan 1
anyway.
So this is how we are
creating this data set
for training the
model to teaching
it to think
maximally in parallel
and generate those plans.
If the model wants to go
back and reverse on a plan,
it still can do that.
It still sees all
of these contexts.
It's just like the model
is trained to think more
in parallel.
And also because it's
trained to be like that,
and we have this special tags,
or ways of the model generating
these plans and
execution plans, we
can act on it and leverage
those parallelism.
Yes.
Is the plan to change the
structure of this LLM,
because before, you just need
to predict the next token,
but now you seem to have
three parallel lines?
It's always next open.
It's just that there is
instead of everything, the plan
and execution, one at a time,
if there is a tag like here,
this is plan i, and
here are the execution.
And here is plan 2,
plan i and i plus 1.
For example, here is
plan 1 and plan plus 2.
This is the high level count.
And then now that we know that
there are these two plans,
we can just branch out
and run them in parallel.
So that's the idea here.
So here is the training
recipe starting from--
so we generate 6k thinking
trajectories for MATH data set.
We keep the ones with
higher parallelization,
and we do supervised fine tuning
on DeepSeek-R1 Distill-Qwen-7B
on this reformatted
trajectories.
And the interesting
property that we observed
was that, so when we
started the project,
the goal was to
maximize parallelism
for reducing the sequential
token generation,
so we save on that.
But it turns out this process
actually helps out with accuracy
as well.
The model seems to like these
more structured way of thinking,
and this way of
encouraging parallelism
helps the model have
higher accuracy as well.
And here, what we are showing
that is the average number
of sequential tokens over
the baseline model like R1
Distill-7B.
And the SPRINT model,
again, is distilling R1.
This basically, there we are
fine tuning the 7B model,
and there's a big jump like
a 3 and 1/2% jump over that,
while also becoming much more
efficient than a 32B in terms
of number of sequential tokens.
Like you said, there's
[INAUDIBLE] and more opportunity
to explore more approaches
given the fixed compute budget,
because--
It could be, yeah.
And we have some
data on that, which
I believe I'm going to show.
The model does explore more
and think in parallel more.
And another
interesting observation
was that we have out of
domain generalization as well.
So the training to
think in parallel
was done for the MATH
data set, but we also
saw the model is doing better.
Not only have more opportunities
for this parallelism, but also
higher accuracy, for example,
countdown or GPQA diamond data
set, so there is no training.
We have not trained
on those data sets,
but the model generalizes.
And this could go back to
what you were suggesting,
that the model can
think in parallel.
And that inherently
seems to help the model,
but as a side effect, we
also have opportunities
for leveraging this parallelism
and reducing the number
of sequential tokens.
Could there be a scenario, where
individually, the answers are
correct in parallel branches,
but when you combine it,
say in a sequential manner,
the answer may be wrong,
and in that case, what
will take precedence?
And in that case--
What will take precedence?
Because sometimes, even in
a mathematical equation,
individually, when you
look at them in isolation,
the answer might look
seemingly correct,
but when you put all
the steps together,
the answer may
eventually be wrong.
So when the model
generates, no matter
if it generates
sequentially, or in parallel,
at the end of the
day, everything
is condensed into the context,
so the model sees that.
And this is the
thinking process.
The answer, after
this, the model
should generate a
synthesized final answer,
so if there are contradictions
in the sequential,
or in parallel, the
model is expected
to resolve that before
generating a final answer.
So in that case, it's
a little difficult
to say because both approaches
can suffer from contradictions
in the thinking.
But here, what we are seeing is
more that these plans are rather
than being different approaches
to solve the same problem,
they're different steps
to solve one problem.
So another interesting
observation was that--
and perhaps intuitive
some that harder problems
require more iterative
planning and execution.
The other observation-- this was
maybe less intuitive was that
in the early stages--
so we have a bunch of these
parallel planning execution,
parallel planning execution.
In the early stages, the more
parallelism, or more exploration
is observed by the model,
and then in the later stages,
we converge to
maybe to less plans.
Basically, the exploration
is more in the early stages,
and towards the end, we
want to really go dive deep
into a single plan
and execution.
Yes.
How can you ensure that
the independent reasoning
tasks are evenly load
balanced and do not
encounter bottlenecks?
Do independent
tasks, for example,
have similar expected
execution times?
Here, you are saying
that how do we make sure?
So when we divide
independent tasks,
how do we ensure that these
are going to be executed
in about similar times?
So the question is,
how do we ensure
that these
independent plans that
are now run at the same time,
they take similar times?
So the thing is we
can ensure that.
There are some measures
taken to enable that,
but we still could
have a straggler.
Maybe step 2 versus
4 here, step 4
may take a lot longer than
step 2, but at the same time,
we are confined to just step 4,
not step 4 plus step 2 runtime.
And we have some measures.
For example, if the
execution is just too simple,
we merge that into
the plan and try
to create these bigger
and bigger chunks
that we can do in parallel, but
that could be an optimization
as well, the optimizing
this across the stages.
So I was wondering
if there's a group
analysis for it [INAUDIBLE]?
I'm not sure.
I'm not sure if there's
analysis exactly on that.
Question?
Yes.
Could you go back to the slide?
So I saw on the MATH
and GPQA, the SPRINT
has comparable
accuracy and number
of tokens as the baseline.
So I'm curious, for
those benchmarks,
what is the mean
width of the tree,
and what's the maximum width?
In terms of because
the width of the tree
determines how much
parallelism you can exploit.
So what you're getting
at is that the width is
task-dependent, basically?
Yeah.
The parallelism that we can
exploit, and for some of these,
basically if the ratio
of the sequential tokens
is for one task.
For example, I believe, for MATH
is lower than for GPQ domain,
then yes, that's an
indication of parallelism.
Some tasks could be inherently
more parallel than the other.
And I don't know the exact
number of the width of the tree
here, but that to be able
to leverage this approach,
parallelism should exist.
But what we observed
is that that
is the case for many of the
reasoning problems like MATH
and other reasoning
tasks in GPQA and so on.
And some of these are--
again, for example, if you look
at this for the MATH data set
compared to some of
these methods with even
lower, but comparable accuracy,
we are increasing the bandwidth,
or reducing the number
of sequence token
by something like 40%, which
is a long, large number.
But it is true that this is
going to be task-dependent.
And maybe getting back
to your questions,
we have larger
savings for problems
that need more thinking.
So for example,
here we are showing
the sequential token reduction
by SPRINT over the baseline.
Sorry, over the RFT model.
This is the rejection
fine tuning methods,
so this is a baseline
we are comparing with.
If the number of tokens in
generated, like in the thinking
process is small, then there
is probably less opportunity
for parallelism.
So by doing this, oh, let's
plan and execute, actually,
we can be worse
than the baseline.
But this appears in the
harder problems and problems
that require more thinking and
more number of parallel tokens,
and that's where this method
shines and shows in parallelism.
I'm not sure how many of you
have read the recent Sonnet 4.5
system card, but it was very
interesting to me that it says,
the prompt for the
system card encourages
the model to use tools as much
as possible, and, at least,
100 times.
That's a very large
number that the model
is encouraged to use the tool.
And this just shows that we are
going into this regime that we
are solving more and more
interesting problems,
and we are actually going
more and way beyond 8 to 10k,
even for the number of tokens
that the model deals with
for solving a problem.
Yes.
So can you come back to the
fine tuning of data set diagram
with all the trees?
Fine tuning process.
I think one.
Yeah, there.
Doing inference, does it
reduce the entire step 1
to step k the entire thing,
but different layers,
or does it do a sequential?
No.
During inference,
it just likes this.
So the model learns
to generate plans
that can be executed in
parallel at the same time,
so it first generates
plan 1 and 2,
and then once plan 1 is
outputted, execution of plan 1
starts.
Once plan 2 is outputted,
execution of plan 2
starts, then the result is
put back in the context,
and then the model is
generating two more plans.
So the model still takes
this sequential approach
to generating plans
and execution,
but the difference is that
if it learns, or is trained
to at each point of time,
if there are plans that
can be executed in
parallel, it generates
those at the same time.
So here, would be
after step 1, it
generates step 2 and
4 at the same time,
and then you see the results
for that and then so on
and it continues.
So think about it, each
step is a plan and a set
of executions in the training.
But this step here is
defined as plan 1 and exit 1,
and then it be changed
the notion of--
Do they also match this?
So let's say, they execute two
plans that can be parallelized,
and then they
collect the context
and then add it to the
prompt for the next level.
Do they also do that
in the training phase
as well to match how
they are proping it?
This is how the training
data will look like.
So plan 1 and 2 are
independent, so plan 1 and 2
are put together
next to each other,
and then we have execution
1 and 2 during training.
So that's how the model
sees during training
that plan 1 and 2 could
be outfitted together,
but at inference, the
execution is actually
also done in parallel.
Let's move on to the
last paper because I want
to make sure we cover that.
But just before
that, opportunity.
So here, the work that
supervised fine tuning,
but, of course, methods like RL
and GRPO can enable potentially
much more benefit from
this data and much
more this
generalization property
usually works well with RL.
And other notions about
tool use, overlapping
different tools, or actually
realizing the wall clock speed
of this other work
that can be done here
in the implementation
of this method.
So now, let's go through
another method called SWiRL.
This is also a continuation
of multi-step synthetic data
generation and helping the
model do multi-step better.
And this is a work that
is going to be presented
next week at COLM in
Conference in Language
Modeling in Montreal.
So this is another
just a preview.
This is another training.
We are using training
and basically
fine tuning a language
model to help it
do multi-step reasoning better.
So motivation, again,
many real world tasks
require multi-step
reasoning and tool use.
For example, if you want to
answer multi-hop question using
a search engine, you want
to solve math problems,
or use solving a software
engineering like doing
a project, planning a trip,
analyzing data, and so on.
Usually, we go as humans,
we use these tools,
and reason through them for
important tasks more than one,
so we need a cohesive number
of steps of reasoning and tool
use in order to solve a problem.
So the challenges, again, in
multi-step reasoning and tool
use setting is that then you're
doing reasoning and tool use.
Even for one step, it
can get complicated,
but as we expand on
this and generate
multiple steps of
reasoning and tool use,
the errors and the
complications can compound
over these different steps.
If we want the model to-- and
another focus of this paper
is enabling tool use,
like teaching the model
to use the right tools,
for example, a calculator,
Python executor, and so on.
Using these tools live
during the training process
can be very challenging
because tools can fail,
they can be slow, and the
training process is already
time consuming and challenging,
so this can further
slow that down.
And if you look back in terms
of the fine tuning processes,
such as reinforcement
learning from human feedback,
from AI feedback, or execution
feedback, many of these
are optimized for
single step tasks.
Basically, the model takes a
lot of whatever it wants to do,
generates a final
answer, and the reward
is just based on the final
answer, whether it's correct
or not, and then we back
propagate that towards actions.
And here, we want to
have more of governance
on the process of
generating these steps
and how we can optimize them.
So this framework called SWiRL,
and the design goal for SWiRL
is the following.
First of all, at
a high level, we
want the model to solve complex
problem and multi-step reasoning
task.
We want the model to
know when to call a tool,
generate the right
queries to invoke a tool,
because we need to
know how to use a tool,
the model needs to know that,
carry out these reasoning steps
and maintain
accuracy across them,
and learn how to
recover from an error
and learn when to stop taking
new steps and calling new tools,
and say, OK, I'm now ready
to generate a final answer,
so we want the model
to know these steps.
We also want to avoid using
tools during the training
process, because like I
mentioned, this can be slow.
Tools can fail, and can have
bugs, so we want to avoid that.
And ideally, we want the
model to generalize this,
so ideally, we want
the model to learn
when to adapt to new tools
and new reasoning tasks
and capabilities.
So to approach this,
here is the process.
The first step of this process
is that let's start with
creating synthetic
multi-step data for a model,
so given a prompt--
and in order to really
annotate these steps,
let's have the model
take one step at a time
and let the model know at each
step that it's free to reason,
create a chain of
thought, call a tool,
or propose a final answer.
So having an input prompt at
step 1, we tell the model,
you have access to
these tools, you
can generate a reasoning step.
If you're ready to
generate the final answer,
just say that and create that.
So given this prompt, the model
would take the first action,
which could be a reasoning
step followed by a tool call,
and then we show the model
the environment response.
So given that, then we show the
model again the same prompt,
but this time, we have the
context from the previous step.
So basically, we say, here
is the original prompt,
here is the previous
action, and here is
the result of taking that
action from the environment.
You can take a new
action and call
a tool, or if you're ready to
create a final answer, just
output the final answer.
So by design, through this
adapt to iterative prompting,
we are creating this
multi-step data set,
and the steps can
be from 1 to 3 or 5,
and so on for different queries.
Then we need a label.
We want to have a notation
of how good this step is,
and to do so, we ask
an LLM-as-a-Judge,
given the prior context
and the current action,
which is a reasoning step,
followed by a tool called,
give us a reward function, or
give us your estimate of how
good this trajectory
and final action is.
Given that we have for each
query and we have a set
of steps, and for each step, we
have a LLM-as-a-Judge score that
is assigned to that step.
And we can do that offline.
We can go through many, many
questions in parallel offline
and generate these steps
and labeled annotations.
Once we have these
steps per prompt,
we can filter this
data in different ways.
For example, we can
only keep the data,
where the LLM-as-a-Judge decided
every single step was a good
step.
Every single action was good.
Or we can go based on
outcome filter data,
and that would be we
keep all the trajectories
that the final answer was
correct, no matter what
the label per step was.
And we're going to see how these
two differed with each other.
But the whole intuition,
motivation behind this part
is that, for these
reasoning prompts, we
have a number of steps,
and then for each step,
we have a reward created by
the model, which we can use
or not use during our
training, but let's
see how these two play out.
Then having this data that
we have generated offline,
we can start the
training process,
and the training in
this part is done based
on reinforcement learning.
So maybe you can pay attention
to this figure on the right.
This is a very simple example,
but let's go through that.
Who is older, Glenn, I
don't know the last name,
or Ross Lynch?
So these two people,
who is older?
So action 1 is to
figure out who is older.
I should first search for
age of the first person.
Then we have a reward
for this action.
We ask the judge, LLM-as-a-Judge
to say given an input prompt
and this action, what is
the reward for this step?
Then we actually go and show the
model the result of this step.
This is already we have
in our training data,
so we have the
environment response,
and then we prompt the model
to take the next action.
And then the next action
is this second question,
which is about the age
of the second person.
We have a reward based on that.
And at the last stage
we say, given the result
of the previous searches,
we asked the model
to generate another action.
In this case, the
model seems to be
ready to output
the final answer,
so it outputs the answer
in these tags answer
and the final answer
is there, and we
can get a reward based on that.
So the point that I want
you to pay attention to
is how we manage to not have
the tool calls during training.
So basically, what
we are doing here
is that we have this
trajectory from the prompt
and from these pre-collected
actions and tool calls.
During RL process,
we get the reward.
We show the prompt and steps
and actions onto that action k,
in this case, for example, up
to action 1 and the environment
response, and then we ask the
model to take the next step.
So this is the part that
is done during training.
The model takes the
next action, but we
don't need to execute that
action or call the tool.
We just collect the reward
based on that specific action
and use that for
RL optimization.
All the tool calls are just
done during the data annotation
process outside of the
RL fine tuning part.
Because we realize that the
LLM just does a good job based
on the quality of the
action that's proposed,
we're good in just
evaluating that.
We don't need to execute the
action and evaluate that.
So that's how we
separated the two.
Do you need to train LLM
Judge with this for use?
So we did not train an
LLM-as-a-Judge for this.
We just prompted--
I'll talk about what models
we used for each one, so there
was no training for that.
But if you the judge cannot see
the real output from the tool
use, how do you [INAUDIBLE]?
So the question is if the
judge cannot see the output
of the tool, how can it
give a reasonable score?
So here's the point here.
So we are asking
the judge to judge
the quality of the query that
is generated by the model
to call the tool, rather
than the output of the tool.
Like here, what the judge
sees is that the model
is asking age of this person.
And the model can judge
that this is a good question
to create for the search
engine before seeing
the result of the search engine.
The model doesn't need to know
the age of this person to know
this question was good or bad.
This is a good question.
This is a reasonable question.
So basically, what we are
doing is providing this process
feedback, process
reward for this step,
and the tool calls are
captured in the prior context.
So all of these
tool call resources,
we have collected them in our
offline training data set.
We are not doing that during
the actual RL fine tuning.
So to just show you the
objective function that
is being optimized in
this multi-step RL is,
let's say we have a number
of steps S1 to SK, and then
for each followed by an
action, which is a reasoning
step followed by a tool call.
What we are doing
here is that we
are optimizing the expected
reward of a single action, given
all the context so far, which
is a set of states and actions
that we have collected also.
So that's how we are
optimizing the expected reward
of a single action in
a multi-step process,
given all the prior
steps, but, of course,
this varies from action 1
all the way to action K.
Now, during inference
once we RL this model,
let's walk through
an inference process
of how we encourage the model
to do this multi-step process.
So, for example,
here the prompt is
help me answer the following
questions in just a few words.
And then we specify the
tool that the model can use,
in this case, a calculator.
If you think it would
help to use a calculator,
please generate a
mathematical query
enclosed by these kind of tags.
And then we also tell
the model, once you
have enough information, you
can generate an answer tag
and generate the final answer.
So through these tags, the
model can tell us the tool call,
or if it's ready to
generate the final answer.
So here is the input question.
So in step 1, the
model is prompted.
Here is the input question,
the model responses
to that question.
And in this response is
calling it the calculator,
and it's calling this is the
math that it wants to run.
The user provides that output.
Basically, that tool is
executed with that given input.
We give the output to the
model, and then the model
is prompted again.
Again, here is the input.
Here is the result from the
previous thinking process
and tool call, and the
model takes the next action,
and next action and so far.
So we are iteratively
prompt the model.
Here is what happens so far.
Here is the tool you have.
If you're ready to generate
the final answer, do it.
If not, continue using the tool.
So the experimental setup for
this approach was the following.
There is a model Gemma-2-27b
was used to create
this multi-step synthetic data.
The questions were coming
from HotPotQA and GSM8k.
We had something like
50k sourced from a number
of problems and created for
different kinds of data that
were, like I said, we can
process this data that we
created based on process filter,
outcome filtered both process,
and outcome filtered or random.
And then we also collected a
number of trajectories, I think.
So let's take a look at
impact of data filtering
on the performance of SWiRL.
One perhaps in the beginning,
this was non-intuitive,
but we realized why
this is happening
is that it seems like when our
training data was only processed
filtered, meaning we
took reasoning steps that
were majority like voted
yes by LLM as a Judge
from the reasoning
steps, but we like
didn't filter them based on the
correctness of final answer.
This seems to help the training
more than if we rigorously
only took trajectories where
the outcome was correct,
or both process and
outcome were correct.
And the reason for that is
if we only get trajectories,
where the model already knows
the outcome and is correct,
perhaps you're not helping
the model solve problems
that it couldn't solve
during test time,
because we are training
it to think differently
about these problems, so
it can solve new problems
that it couldn't solve before,
but it had gotten the sum
processes correctly.
But perhaps the
most interesting,
and this is, again,
something that we
are seeing in the
SPRINT project as well,
is the generalization
performance of the model.
So for example, we
had SWiRL on GSM8k.
These are MATH problems, and
we were teaching the model
to use SymPy, a
calculator basically,
to solve these problems.
So that was the training data.
And then once we do this
multi-step optimization using
GSM8k, we then
tested on HotPotQA.
And this is the
accuracy that increase
that we get from the base
model, so it goes from 65 to 71.
And if we were to use exactly
HotPotQA, and in this case,
the tool for HotPotQA was a
search tool, not a calculator,
the increase was from 65 to 73.
So and vice versa,
this was true as well.
If we train the model on
HotPotQA with a search tool,
it could also do well
on GSM8k with Python.
So it seems like there is
something going beyond just
like learning to use a
specific tool, rather,
the model is learning
how to think in steps
and how to learn how
to invoke a tool.
And these data sets,
the other data sets
are separate from any
of our training data.
Another important observation
here was that, again,
in this case, the model is
being trained on HotPotQA
using a search tool
for all of these,
but we are showing
the test results
as we are increasing the
synthetic data, the training
data size.
So it seems like as we go from
100 training examples to 10,000
training examples,
even at inference,
the model is improving on a
completely different task,
which is MATH
problems and GSM8k.
So this is, again, it's the most
important graph from this paper
showing that by creating
synthetic data in environments
that are perhaps easier
to create these data for,
and teaching the model
how to use these tools
and how to do things
in multiple steps,
we can generalize these
behavior to entirely new tools
and domains.
And perhaps, scaling
this up could
be a very powerful methodology.
And here, we are
showing some results
to try to interpret why the
model is becoming better
in through this RL processes.
And what we did here is to
look into the average process
reward per step of
the model in answering
these questions before
and after being fine
tuned through this
reinforcement learning process.
And perhaps this is,
again, very intuitive
that the process
correctness of the model
has improved
throughout this process
for both in-distribution
domain, where
we train on HotPotQA,
and out of distribution
when we just tested on GSM8k.
So the model thinks more
correctly per step, both for
on the training data, but
out of distribution data.
And here are some other
results that we also
looked into precision,
recall, and other metrics
across a number of tasks.
And here are how this works
compared to frontier models.
Something that perhaps
is worth noting here
is that we could do all of this.
That all of this process
that we did with RL,
we could do it with supervised
fine tuning as well,
and it turns out that this
multi-step RL does better
by a good amount over
supervised fine tuning.
And especially for
supervised fine tuning,
it seems like the
model really benefited,
like the training data
needed to be correct,
both process and
outcome filtered.
Supervised finding on
that kind of training data
worked better than
when we selected
only the process filtered data.
And it makes sense because
in supervised fine tuning,
it's an imitation learning.
We are showing these
are the trajectories,
and we want the model to
repeat those in a way.
And then if they're
incorrect, the outcome
is incorrect, it might
hurt performance,
whereas in RL, we are giving
the model a new chance
to take a new action
within the prior steps.
And we are giving a reward
based on that new action,
and that's how it can
break out from this.
And here are some other results,
but because we are out of time,
let's just take a look
at the summary of this.
So again, a
important observation
was that soil of generalizes
across data sets and tools.
It transfers to disparate task,
and the model learns better
from process filtered data,
and it can get a lot of gains
from more synthetic data, both
for in domain and out of domain.
And from just understanding
why this happens,
it turns out that
after this fine tuning,
the process correctness
of the model
improves, so if we just
go to evaluate that,
the model becomes better at
this multi-step thinking.
Again, this is true for
both in-distribution and out
of distribution data.
And with that, we can
conclude this lecture.
I hope you learned more about
multi-step and reasoning
and planning, which is
a very active field that
is going forward.